Welcome. Today's דף daf is ל"ה, Lamed Heh, 35. Welcome to כיצד
מברכין Kaitzad Mevarkhim and what I consider to be like the second
half of the מסכת, masechet, not only because it's a little bit
about halfway in, but because the first half is really about the
daily liturgy, שמע Shema and שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh, and now from
this point on, we talk about ברכות brachot that appear at various
times during the day but not part of like a fixed liturgy.
And of course the primary focus is the ברכות brachot before and
after eating, and then later we get to other ברכות, brachot, you
know, that might come up during the day. So let's start now
with the משנה mishna on the top of ל"ה עמוד א'. Lamed
Heh Amud Aleph. כיצד מברכין על הפירות, Kaitzad mevarkhin al haperot, how
do you make a blessing over the fruit? על פירות האילן הוא
אומר בורא פרי העץ, Al perot ha-ilan hu omer borei pri ha-etz,
for fruit from the tree you say, blessed are You God, creator
of the fruit of the tree. חוץ מן היין, chutz min hayayin,
as except from wine, for the blessing over wine, שעל היין הוא
אומר בורא פרי הגפן. she-al hayayin hu omer borei pri hagefen. Blessed
are You who creates the fruit of the vine. I should mention
that implicit, already assumed in this משנה, mishna, is that you would
make the ברכה bracha בורא פרי העץ borei pri ha-etz in the
fruit when it's in its different form. So the fact that it
was a juice, turned, a fruit turned into a juice, we would
have assumed you make a בורא פרי העץ, borei pri ha-etz, and
it has to tell me, no, that you go ahead and for
wine is a case where you'll even make a special ברכה bracha
of בורא פרי הגפן. borei pri hagefen. Yes, Charlie?
What is the significance of
the different Hebrew words
אילן ilan and עץ etz referring
to the tree?
Oh, that's an interesting question. I mean עץ, etz, as you know,
literally can mean wood but it also means tree.
You know, yes please? It's biblical versus rabbinic. לשון מקרא lashon mikra
and לשון חכמים. lashon chakhamim. אילן ilan doesn't appear in the מקרא.
mikra. So when they עץ פרי עשה פרי למינו, etz pri oseh
pri le-mino,
when they
composed ברכות brachot they use Shakespearean Hebrew. Well, I would say that
that is correct, meaning that it is worth, so thank you very
much for that, and it is worthy to note that yes, the
language of ברכות brachot very much draws on the language of the
פסוקים. psukim. So for example, where you really see this coming to
fore is by the ברכות brachot in the, I think in the
שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh for the
רגלים. regalim. Because there, whatever popular name we give to the חגים,
chagim, in the ברכה bracha it is always the language of the
מקרא. mikra. חג המצות, Chag HaMatzot, we don't call פסח, Pesach, right?
We call it, you know, you know, we might say זמן מתן
תורתנו, Zman Matan Toratenu, but that's not what we actually say in
the חתימה chatima of the ברכה bracha because it's never called מתן
תורתנו, Matan Toratenu, you know, in the תורה. Torah.
And that's why some ספרדים Sefardim do not say בורא פרי הגפן,
borei pri hagafen, they say בורא פרי הגפן, borei pri hagefen, because
the form גפן gafen does not appear in the תנ"ך. Tanakh. Wait
a minute, the difference between גפן gafen and גפן gefen is whether
it's the end of a פסוק pasuk or
not the end of a פסוק. pasuk.
But it doesn't appear גפן gafen as such, it never appears in
the תנ"ך Tanakh as the final word. So the מחלוקת machloket is
grammatically you should say גפן gafen because it's the end of your,
if you apply biblical grammar. But the other side says that no,
we only use the form that's used in the תנ"ך.
Tanakh. Interesting, I never heard that. I never heard that. That's fascinating.
But yes, thank you very much Joe for that. That's absolutely correct
that the ברכות, brachot, particularly the חתימה chatima of the ברכה bracha
is very much biblical language.
When do we get to, maybe the גמרא gemara talks about it,
you're supposed to say a ברכה bracha after you eat?
Yeah, so all of this will be in the גמרא. gemara. How
do you know you say before, how do you know you say
after? It's all going to be the first thing the גמרא gemara
will address. Okay, so thank you for that. So okay. The other
thing to note is of course we're not saying you create the
wine because the גמרא gemara says God didn't create the wine. Human
beings did. I mean at least through humans but it involved human
process. So therefore even when we make a special ברכה bracha on
the wine which is, you know, in this new form, we still
refer to its natural form and we
say בורא פרי הגפן. borei pri hagefen. ועל פירות הארץ הוא אומר
בורא פרי האדמה, ve-al perot ha-aretz hu omer borei pri ha-adama, for
fruit of the land you say, creator of the fruit of the
land, of the dirt, of the earth.
וחוץ מן הפת, ve-chutz min hapat, except for bread, again assuming that
you make the same ברכה bracha in a changed form. So but
bread, don't say בורא פרי האדמה, borei pri ha-adama, I mean it
does come from wheat. Wheat grows, you know, if you ate wheat
you'd say בורא פרי האדמה borei pri ha-adama if you're not saying
שהכל she-hakol if you're eating it in a normal way. But by
bread don't say בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri ha-adama. There you say,
הוא אומר המוציא לחם מן הארץ. hu omer hamotzi lechem min ha-aretz.
God takes bread out of the land. Now there it is, does
get sort of close to this idea of like the finished product
because it's לחם. lechem. God really doesn't bring bread out of the
land, God brings wheat out of the land. So we are basically
making reference to the finished product, but still we are focusing on
the divine act of creating the wheat and not focusing on the
human process of making it into bread.
But wait a minute, but
God doesn't make the bread. I know. So we obviously have both
elements
here, yes.
What
about rice bread, people cannot eat wheat.
What? No, it's okay. What?
People can't eat wheat. Right. Like my wife. If we can't say
המוציא לחם מן הארץ hamotzi lechem min ha-aretz on rice bread, then
we can never get to make המוציא.
hamotzi. So, all right, I mean that might be true, but we'll
talk about that. But there's also spelt.
Jewish פת Pat party?
No, פת Pat is פת Pat from the five species of grain.
Limited to... No, it's limited to the five species. So, because we
interpret one of those species to be spelt, which is debated, but
spelt as far as I understand... what?
The people that can't eat spelt.
Wait, can't they eat one of them? Can they eat spelt, rye?
Spelt is a form of wheat.
Wait a minute, there's spelt, rye, what's the other one? Oats, barley,
and wheat are
off-limits, oats, barley, rye, spelt.
I thought that there were people who could not eat... I don't
disagree with you that
spelt is low gluten, it's lower than flour, but it does contain...
okay, wow. Okay.
So, all right, so we will talk.
All right, we'll talk about fine. We'll talk about all of it.
והירקות הוא אומר Ve'hayarakot hu omer and for vegetables he says בורא
פרי האדמה Borei Peri Ha'adama creator of the fruit of the ground.
Now, so which is the same as you said for what he
called fruit of... what it referred to פירות הארץ. Peirot Ha'aretz. So
what's the difference between פירות הארץ Peirot Ha'aretz fruit of the earth
and vegetables? Right? What are fruit... there're two different things you make
בורא פרי האדמה Borei Peri Ha'adama for. So presumably, fruit of the
earth are things that grow above the ground, meaning, you know, there's
different ways of defining what the Gemara's different categories are, but one
I would just suggest is that things that grow above the ground
are פרי הארץ, Peri Ha'aretz, you know, they're not פרי העץ, Peri
Ha'etz, but they are like fruit, they grow out of the ground,
but they grow above the ground as opposed to vegetables which grow
in the ground.
So רש"י Rashi also though mentions, when רש"י Rashi mentions, right, so
that's... but רש"י Rashi for a minute. ורבי יהודה אומר Ve'rabbi Yehuda
omer and Rabbi Yehuda says by this last category you don't make
בורא פרי האדמה Borei Peri Ha'adama on both. On this last category
you say בורא מיני דשאים. Borei Minei Deshaim. You make types of
herbs or literally grasses, which suggests also that this category of vegetables
is not limited to things below the ground. רש"י Rashi says it
includes things like
קטניות. Kitniyot. Right, like legumes. So if it includes
legumes, so legumes are vegetables, so what's... so what's פירות הארץ? Peirot
Ha'aretz? I mean clearly it's like tall standing things like the grains.
Does it include more than the grains? According to this idea that
you divide things into פירות הארץ Peirot Ha'aretz and vegetables, it's a
little bit unclear. We will discuss that as we continue in the
גמרא. Gemara. So what you have here is a laying out of
the various categories of what you make. There's no discussion about how
we know you make them. What is clear is with a few
things that do emerge from here are, number one, that you differentiate
the types of ברכות Berachot based on the things that you're eating,
which of course we take for granted, but needs to be said.
Then there's going to be a normal question which is, in addition
to the question of what text do the Rabbis assign, you know,
there's the question about how do we as human beings categorize things?
Right? What type of categories do we naturally assign to different things?
I mean if you're a botanist, right, if you ask somebody, you
know, what's a tomato, they'll say it's a vegetable. You ask a
botanist, they'll say it's a fruit because it's got seeds. You know,
it's got seeds on the inside of it. It makes it a
fruit, not a vegetable. But we tend to treat it as a...
you know... it makes it a fruit, but we tend to treat
it as a vegetable because it's not sweet and it's not, you
know, it doesn't grow from a tree. So how do you generally
categorize things? How, you know, it's a question, you know, within any
given society what categories it creates for something. Then there's the question
about how הלכה Halacha chooses to categorize things. Which boxes does הלכה
Halacha put it in? And then does it assign different blessings to
each of those boxes? In this משנה Mishnah we see that it
has a category called פרי העץ, Peri Ha'etz, פרי הארץ, Peri Ha'aretz,
and has another category called vegetables, ירקות. Yarakot. And at least according
to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma it assigns the same ברכה Beracha
for both. So we see a differentiation of ברכות, Berachot, but we
see that and based on categories, but not all categories get different
ברכות. Berachot. We also see that implicitly that a changed form will
at least in many cases presumably will retain the same ברכה. Beracha.
And nevertheless, wine and bread are made as an exception, which get
a special ברכה Beracha when they exist in those particular forms. Yes.
But doesn't it surprise you that the first categories of food in
a shepherding society are agricultural?
Interesting. I assume that the משנה Mishnah is starting from the more
specific to the more general. Because when you're going to end with
the ברכה Beracha of meat and milk and so on, you're going
to be שהכל. Shehakol. ושהכל Ve'shehakol includes... is a ברכה Beracha that's
a catch-all. The same way it moves from העץ Ha'etz to האדמה.
Ha'adama. If you said האדמה Ha'adama on something you should have said
העץ Ha'etz in, האדמה Ha'adama includes it. So the way I see
the משנה Mishnah sort of moving is moving from the more particular
to the more general.
Thank you.
Yes. But that wasn't your question.
Well, no, but it does sound like perhaps their food products were
much more agricultural than
for us. Than from a shepherding...
okay, that I don't know. Meaning I don't know that the order
here has to do with the frequency in which it's being eaten.
I mean if the question is why is שהכל Shehakol a catch-all?
Why don't you be more specific about things like meat and eggs
and milk and more general... About these types of things, I mean
I think that has to do with the fact about, you know,
the degree to which you sort of like identify—I don't know—like identify
God's sort of direct role in their production, more something that's a
little bit more obvious by the agricultural products and it is by
the animals, you know, on that role.
Right. You'd imagine, I would've assumed, see an economic base in shepherding
and dietary based in products of shepherding, milk and meat. You would
assume, I would have assumed, that that's where they would've started.
This might reflect the fact
that they're much more...
Right,
I hear the point.
I'm just saying I'm not sure that that would've dictated the order
in which these are addressed, but I hear the point. Okay.
At the time
of the משנה, Mishnah,
they're agriculturally—they're agriculturally based, I think. Yeah.
Let's also not forget that ברכות Berachot appears in זרעים, Zeraim, which
is about agriculture. So obviously that's going to dictate a lot also.
Literally seeds. Exactly. So let's take a look now at the גמרא.
Gemara. מנא הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? Where is this all from
that you make ברכות Berachot at the beginning? דתנו רבנן, Detanu rabanan,
our rabbis taught: קודש הלולים לה'. Kodesh hilulim l'Hashem. This is about
נטע רבאי, Netai Revai, about things in their third year—three years you
can't eat the fruit of the trees, it's ערלה. Orlah. Fourth year
you bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim and you eat it there, sort
of like מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. And the פסוק Pasuk says that
it will be קודש הלולים לה', Kodesh hilulim l'Hashem, sanctified like a
praising, singing to God. So what does this mean, הלולים לה'? Hilulim
l'Hashem? מלמד שטעונין ברכה לפניהם ולאחריהם. Melamed shete'unin bracha lifneihem u'leachareihem. So
how do you—so you sing to God about your food? So you
praise God before and after. So that's how you learn that you
make a ברכה Bracha before and after. Now you're saying why don't
you do after? You have ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. But after is
only by certain things, by bread, maybe the שבעת המינים, Shivat Haminim,
right? How do you know you make all ברכות Berachot by all
foods after? So you get it from here. מלמד שטעונין ברכה לפניהם
ולאחריהם. Melamed shete'unin bracha lifneihem u'leachareihem. מתנה אמר רבי עקיבא, Mitana amar
Rabbi Akiva, but here says Rabbi Akiva: אסור לאדם שיטעום כלום קודם
שיברך. Assur l'adam sheyitom klum kodem sheyivarech. It is forbidden for a
person to taste anything before they make a blessing. Now that idea
forbidden seems to strike a different note than the need to give
thanks and praise to God. You might say חייב אדם לברך קודם
שיאכל, Chayav adam livarech kodem sheyochal, you're obligated to bless, but the
idea that it is forbidden seems to point to a different concern
or a different issue around ברכות, Berachot, which we will get to
in just a little bit, which I'm sure people are familiar with.
Just... can we go back to the פסוק? Pasuk? Just—yes. I think
it explains this a little bit better, because it says שלוש שנים
יהיה לכם ערלים לא יאכל. Shalosh shanim yihiyeh lachem areilim lo ye'achel.
Right. So you can't do it, which seems to almost maybe like,
you know, following the structure of the פסוק. Pasuk. You can't do
it, ובשנה הרביעית יהיה כל פריו קודש הלולים לה', U'vashana harevi'it yihiyeh
kol piryo kodesh hilulim l'Hashem, then you make your praise.
ובשנה הרביעית יהיה כל פריו.
U'vashana harevi'it
yihiyeh kol piryo. Yeah. Yeah. Then you know, so you can't eat
it, you make your ברכה, Bracha, then ובשנה החמישית תאכלו את פריו,
U'vashana hachamishit tochlu et piryo, then you can eat it. So you're
going based on that.
All right. That's nice. So ובשנה החמישית, U'vashana hachamishit, but that could
be—you're right, that Rabbi Akiva's focusing on the not eating that appears
before. I hadn't thought about that. That's a good point. Okay. So
now we have this idea based on this idea of giving praise
to God, but also thrown in this idea that it's forbidden until
that is done. והאי קודש הלולים להכי הוא דאתא? Ve'hai kodesh hilulim
l'hachi hu de'ata? Now the גמרא Gemara questions this. Is that what
it's coming to tell you, this idea that you have to give
praise to God before you eat the fruit? איבעי ליה, Iba'ei lei,
don't we need it to tell me other things? חד, Chad, one,
because הלולים Hilulim is a double language. So from the first double
language you've got a ברכה Bracha before and after. Now we're saying
it's coming to tell me something else. חד אמר רחמנא אחליה ובהדר
אחליה, Chad amar Rachmana achlei u'bahadar achlei, a little play on words.
First the Torah says from the word הלולים Hilulim we're reading the
ה' He like a ח'. Chet. Not only because ה' He and
ח' Chet look similar in the writing except for a little, you
know, hole there in the middle, but also because they're both guttural
languages—we don't appreciate it so much, we don't pronounce them gutturally—but anyway,
so הלולים Hilulim should be read as חילולים, Chillulim, which means to—to
redeem, to transfer the sanctity. So one is to tell you that
the הלכה Halacha of נטע רבאי Netai Revai is like the הלכה
Halacha of מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, that if you don't want to
bring it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you can redeem its value onto money
and bring the money to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So that's what you learn
out from the הלולים. Hilulim. אחליה, Achlei, transfer the value, ובהדר אחליה,
U'bahadar achlei, then you can eat it. Presumably as Michael said, the
next פסוק Pasuk talks about eating it. ואידך, Ve'idach, and the other
הלולים Hilulim it's talking about is דבר הטעון שירה טעון חילול, Davar
hata'un shira ta'un chillul, that only something that you would sing about
has this—is in the category of נטע רבאי. Netai Revai. ושאינו טעון
שירה אינו טעון חילול, Veshe'eino ta'un shira eino ta'un chillul, things that
you don't sing over is not in this category of transferring the
sanctity, is not in the category of נטע רבאי. Netai Revai. What
does that mean, things you sing about and don't sing about? אמר
רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani
amar Rabbi Yochanan, like Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani says, אמר רבי יונתן—excuse
Amar Rabbi Yonatan me—אמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, Amar
Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, מניין שאין אומרים שירה אלא
על היין? Minayin she'ein omrim shira ela al hayayin? How do you
know you only sing over wine? שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it is said,
ותאמר להם הגפן, Vatomer lahem hagefen, a very—a very famous sort of
משל Mashal in the תנ"ך Tanach in שופטים, Shoftim, where it was
a whole sort of critique about who chose to be king. So
as we're all, you know—maybe it's appropriate how in the election year—anyway,
so it had all of the various, you know,
trees arguing about who wants to be king. The basic point was
anybody that had anything worthwhile to be doing was saying "I'm too
busy, you know, growing my fruit to spend my time being king."
So it was only the sort of thorn bush that had nothing
else to do with its time and nothing to contribute that chose
to be king. That's the משל. Mashal. Anyway, so within that משל,
Mashal, here's what it says: ותאמר להם הגפן, Vatomer lahem hagefen, so
the vine said. Have I stopped giving my wine that gladdens
the hearts of God and people that I should now go ahead
and have to have nothing to do with myself other than to
be king? So anyway, wine gladdens the hearts of God and people.
אם אנשים משמח אלוהים במה משמח, im anashim mesameach elohim bemeh mesameach,
if it gladdens the hearts of people says the גמרא, Gemara, how
does it gladden God? So you could have said it gladdens God
by you use it on the altar. Nevertheless, we're going even further
with this idea of משמח. mesameach. מכאן שאין אומרים שירה אלא על
היין. mikan she'ein omrim shira ela al hayayin. You only sing over
the wine. Now what this means in context is that when the
לויים Levi'im sang over the קרבנות, korbanot, they only did it when
the wine was being poured. It's actually quite fascinating: you brought the
entire קרבן, korban, you sprinkled the blood, you slaughtered it, you sprinkled
the blood, you put the limbs on the מזבח mizbeach and they
didn't sing שירה. shira. When did they sing שירה? shira? At the
very end of the process when the wine that came with the
קרבן korban was being poured. אין אומרים שירה אלא על היין. ein
omrim shira ela al hayayin. This also serves as an important model
for הלכה halacha in terms of why we do קידוש Kiddush and
הבדלה Havdalah over wine, that they established rituals of certain types of
praise that was done over wine. אין אומרים שירה אלא על היין
ein omrim shira ela al hayayin and it clearly gives a tremendous
amount of ritual weight to what we do. The proof being that
in the גמרא, Gemara, the only things you do over wine are
קידוש, Kiddush, הבדלה, Havdalah, and ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, whereas what we
have done with what we have, we make a ברכה bracha of
the שבע ברכות Sheva Brachot over wine, we make a ברכת אירוסין
Birkat Erusin over wine, we make a ברכת ברית מילה Birkat Brit
Milah over wine. None of that is in the גמרא, Gemara, but
of course if we didn't do it over wine, it would be
much less of a ritual, right? It gives it a lot of
ritual weight. So anyway, that is the idea that you do these
things over wine and therefore the point being that since הלול hillul
is to praise and praise is wine, that the category of נטע
רבאי Neta Revai of bringing the stuff to ירושלים Yerushalayim in the
fourth year and not eating it, according to this approach, only applies
by wine, by grapes and wine and by nothing else because of
what we learn from this word הלולים. hillulim.
Wait, so here I think this is the first time I've seen
in any way the concept that we make a ברכה bracha because
it makes God happy as opposed to any of the other reasons
one would make a ברכה. bracha.
Well we're not saying that. We're not saying we're saying here that
the wine makes God happy and that's tells you why the לויים
Levi'im sang over the wine. It's not yet tied back to the
ברכה. bracha. This is actually the approach that says we don't learn
ברכה bracha from the word הלול, hillul, we learn other things from
the word הלול. hillul. So there is this idea of making God
happy, that's correct in this context, but it's not about ברכה, bracha,
it's about שירה. shira. So you could say since it's the same
idea of הלול hillul that's used for
ברכות, brachot, there's an indirect connection. That's true. But here the גמרא
Gemara is laying out the opposing approach, says this is not about
ברכות, brachot, it's about wine and on the מזבח mizbeach and that
you only have נטע רבאי Neta Revai by wine. My volume is
slightly low. Okay fine. Okay let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא למאן דתני נטע
רבאי. Haniicha leman detani Neta Revai. That's if it would make sense
if you could learn קודש הלולים kodesh hillulim if normally there's a
basic debate of what is the biblical category of the stuff you
have to bring every fourth year to the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash,
this נטע רבאי. Neta Revai. Is it about basically all plants or
שבעת המינים shivat haminim or whatever, or is it only wine? So
there's a question in all of the משניות mishnayot that discuss this
fourth year that's brought to the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, is the
are the words used in the Tannaitic sources נטע רבאי, Neta Revai,
fourth-year planting, or כרם רבאי, Kerem Revai, fourth year of the vine?
And there's a major debate what is the scope of this biblical
מצוה. mitzvah. So it says you said you need the word הלולים
hillulim to tell you it's limited to wine. Okay, if you generally
reject that and say this category includes all plantings, I understand it's
an extra word and you can use it to teach ברכה. bracha.
הניחא Haniicha so it would work
למאן דתני נטע רבאי, leman detani Neta Revai, if your general words
in the משנה mishnah are נטע רבאי, Neta Revai, so it's not
limited to wine. So then that's not what the verse is doing.
So the verse would come to tell you making ברכות. brachot. אלא
למאן דתני כרם רבאי, Ela leman detani Kerem Revai, but if you
limit the category just to wine that's brought in the fourth year,
מאי איכא למימר, mai ika lemeimar, you can't tell me you use
the verse to tell me ברכה, bracha, you use the verse to
tell me it's a category limited to wine. דאיתמר De'itmar and here's
the debate. It was taught, רבי חייא ורבי שמעון ברבי, Rabbi Chiyya
veRabbi Shimon berebbi, חד תני כרם רבאי, chad tani Kerem Revai, one
says that we always say כרם רבאי, Kerem Revai, it's a category
that only applies to the vine, וחד תני נטע רבאי, vechad tani
Neta Revai, it's planting and it applies to things beyond the vine.
אלא למאן דתני כרם רבאי, Ela leman detani Kerem Revai, now the
גמרא Gemara says, look, even the one that says it's limited to
the vine, I can still say how you get it out of
the פסוק. pasuk. הניחא יליף גזירה שוה. Haniicha yalif gezeirah shavah. Maybe
we get the idea of wine not from this word הלולים hillulim
and singing over wine, but we get the idea of wine limiting
this category from a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. What's the גזירה שוה?
gezeirah shavah? דתניא Detanya as we taught in the ברייתא, braita, רבי
אומר, Rebbi omer, נאמר כאן להוסיף לכם תבואתו. ne'emar kan lehoseif lachem
tevu'ato. Here it says that if you follow these laws of the
ערלה orlah and the fourth year, then you will have an increase
in your grain produce, ונאמר להלן ותבואת הכרם, vene'emar lehalan utevu'at hakerem,
and it says later and the yield of the vine. So you
make
a
גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, תבואה תבואה, tevu'ah tevu'ah, and here
it means... so if you learn vine from somewhere else, the word
here praise will tell you you make a ברכה berakhah? *brachah*. Now,
not now one of the words tells you you have to redeem
it, but at least the other one tells you that there is
a ברכה berakhah? *brachah* here that is associated.
Yes.
How strict in the תלמוד *Talmud* is this notion that you can
only apply the meaning of a word for one thing, you can't
handle multiple interpretations without abandoning other ones?
Right. So that's a good question. I would say the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is pretty strict about that and sometimes it's even, you know,
sometimes in the מדרשי הלכה halakhah. *midreshei halachah* it's even more strict
than that. Sometimes in the מדרשי הלכה halakhah *midreshei halachah* like you
can't start making a דרשה *drashah*, you have to use, you know,
the first instance just for פשט pshat *pshat* and you could only
start making a דרשה *drashah* on later instances of the same type
of a word. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is extremely strict about
that like it says you already used it for this, okay, well
and then it tries to get out of it, it says well
since it could have phrased it a different way and it phrased
it this way, that allows us to say we can still make
a דרשה *drashah*. But the basic principle is very strict. Still there,
yeah. Yeah, yeah, they really are very committed to that. Okay so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, so anyway I got how
you can, you have an extra word of praise if you learn
out vine somewhere else.
But ואי לא יליף גזירה שווה ברכה berakhah מנא ליה *ve-ee lo
yalif gezeirah shavah brachah mina leh*? But if you don't learn the
גזירה שווה *gezeirah shavah* and you limit it to wine, so you
learn it all out from the word הלולים hillulim *hillulim*, where do
you get the idea of a ברכה berakhah *brachah*? And now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, and you know what, even if you do
make a גזירה שווה *gezeirah shavah*. ואי נמי יליף גזירה שווה *ve-ee
nami yalif gezeirah shavah*, even if you get wine from another verse,
so you only get one הילול *hillul*, only one extra idea there
of a blessing. It says הלולים *hillulim*. So הלולים *hillulim*, now one
was to tell you you have to redeem it, right? So we
said הלולים *hillulim*, one tells you you have to redeem it, one
tells you limit it to wine. So now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
says even if you've got an extra word, you're not limiting
it
to wine or you learn it somewhere else, one is already used
up to tell you this principle of doing חילול *chillul*, of to
redeem. So at most the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says you'll get out
of this one ברכה berakhah *brachah*. So therefore אשכחן לאחריו *ashkachan leacharav*.
Therefore it's only one ברכה berakhah *brachah*, we'll just assume that that
ברכה berakhah *brachah* comes at the end because we already have a
precedent for that with ברכת המזון birkat hamazon. *Birkat Hamazon*. So at
most גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says is I'll accept that you can get
one הילול *hillul* out of this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, not two הלולים
*hillulim*. One ברכה berakhah *brachah*. And if it's one ברכה berakhah *brachah*,
it's going to come at the end of the eating, not at
the beginning. So לפניו מניין lefanav minayin, *lefanav minayin*? How would you
know about doing it before? That you could never get to. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says an important point about this, about
the relationship about the ברכה berakhah, *brachah* at the beginning and the
ברכה berakhah. *brachah* at the end. הא לא קשיא ha lo kashya,
*Ha lo kashya*, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
that's not difficult דאתי בקל וחומר dati be'kal vachomer, *de-ati be-kal vachomer*.
You can make a קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer*. If you
make a ברכה berachah, *brachah* at the end, you certainly make it
at the beginning. Why? כשהוא שבע מברך כשהוא רעב לא כל שכן
kshehu save'a mevarech kshehu ra'ev lo kol sheken, *keshehu save'a mevarech keshehu
ra'ev lo kol sheken*? If you make a ברכה berachah *brachah* when
you're sated, when you then how much more so should you make
it when you're hungry? When you're hungry you really appreciate, you know,
you really sort of appreciate how the, you know, the blessing that
God has given you food. You're not so, you know, you're much
more appreciative if you're hungry before you've eaten about what this means
to have this, and after you've eaten, you know, you have experienced
it more. You have more of the experience of getting the blessing
of God, but the appreciation isn't as powerful. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, makes, assumes that if you make a ברכה berachah. *brachah*
after, all the more so you make a ברכה berachah *brachah* before.
But the ברכה berachah *brachah* before is not as important so to
speak.
We assume the ברכה berachah *brachah* before is דרבנן derabbanan, *derabbanan*. Here
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in the end the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will
reject this, but at some stages the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* plays with
the possibility that the ברכה berachah *brachah* before could equally be דאורייתא
*de'oraita* based on this קל וחומר kal vachomer, *kal vachomer*. Now that's
going to be rejected, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does, does play
with that possibility.
I see. My assumption was false, as to say if they learn
something from a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* and not from
a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*.
Oh, I see.
The ברכה berachah *brachah* afterwards is based on interpretation of a פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*.
I see. Even if it's a real קל וחומר *kal vachomer*, because
it's derived it's not as weighty. That doesn't tend to be the
case. I mean the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, you know, קל וחומר
*kal vachomer* is as weighty as a קרא *kra* and so on.
So yeah, that does not seem to be the case. So the
גמרא Mah Gemara *Gemara* here seems to seriously consider that it's דאורייתא
*de'oraita*. Okay, so where we are at this stage is at most
we can get from הלולים *hillulim* one ברכה bracha *brachah*. Maybe it
tells us a ברכה bracha *brachah* at the end and then we'll
get a ברכה bracha *brachah* at the beginning based on a קל
וחומר *kal vachomer*. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now says, okay, אשכחן
כרם kerem *ashkachan kerem*,
fine, but that's limited to vine, to wine. שאר מינין מניין *she'ar
minin minayin*? How do you know other types of food that you
make a ברכה bracha, *brachah* before and after? גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
דילפי מכרם *di-yalpi mikarem*. Okay, well let's learn it out from the
case of the vine. מה כרם kerem, דבר שנהנה וטעון ברכה davar
sheneheneh veta'un berakhah. *Ma kerem davar she-neheneh veta'un brachah*, the same way
vine you derive benefit you make a ברכה bracha, *brachah* before and
after, אף כל דבר שנהנה טעון ברכה davar shehene ta'un berachah, *af
kol davar she-neheneh ta'un brachah*. All other things also we should apply
the same principle. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, איכא למפרך *ika
lemifrach*, you can challenge.
Now here you see as will often happen when the גמרא Gemara
tries to make something a paradigm, it does not necessarily give a
logical reason why you can't apply it elsewhere. It just says if
there's some distinctive characteristic, then who knows, maybe it's connected to the
distinctive characteristic even if there's no logical reason why it should be.
So you want to make a general principle, deriving benefit requires a
ברכה? bracha Maybe it's only by the vine. The vine has special
הלכה. halakhah What special הלכה does the vine have? עוללות, olelot, that
it's one—one of the gifts you leave to the poor is an
unformed cluster. So since that applies to the vine, there's something special.
What does that have to do with making a ברכה? berachah. Nothing.
But because it's something distinctive, maybe therefore this הלכה only applies to
the vine. Okay, so the גמרא says no, קמה תוכיח, kama tochiach,
prove it from grain, because we know you make a ברכה berachah.
after grain because that's ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon, It says ואכלת ושבעת
v'achalta v'savata and speaks there about eating bread. So it says I
can prove there—I can prove from grain, קמה תוכיח, kama tochiach, that
you make a ברכה berachah, by grain, you make a ברכה berachah,
by wine. It's not limited to this law of עוללות. olelot. So
the גמרא says no, מה לקמה שכן חייבת בחלה. mah lekama shekein
chayavet bechallah. Grain has a different distinctive feature that you bring—you separate
חלה challah from it. So yes, we found a ברכה beracha by
wine, we found it by grain, but each one of them is
something distinctive. So it says כרם יוכיח. kerem yochiach. Okay, but the
vine doesn't have חלה. challah. וחזר הדין, vechazar hadin, it goes back,
you know, goes back and forth in a circle. לא ראי זה
כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה, lo rei zeh kerei zeh
velo rei zeh kerei zeh, each one's distinctive characteristic is not like
the other. You can't say it's about עוללות, olelot, that doesn't exist
by grain. You can't say it's about חלה, challah, that doesn't exist
by wine. So those clearly are not the relevant characteristics. הצד השוה
שבהן, hatzad hashaveh shebahen, you have to look at the common side,
the common denominator. What is the common attribute of both of them?
דבר שנהנה וטעון ברכה. beracha. Both of them you're deriving benefit, so
you make a blessing. אף כל דבר שנהנה וטעון ברכה, af kol
davar sheneheneh veta'un berakhah, it should be by everything. So the גמרא
says no, מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן יש בו צד מזבח. mah
lehatzad hashaveh shebahen shekein yesh bo tzad mizbeach. There's a characteristic they
both share that other things do not have. Both of them go
on the מזבח, mizbeach, the altar. You bring grain on the altar
and you bring wine on the altar. And that by the way,
tying into the whole הילולים hillulim and thinking about, you know, eating
and we talk about our table being like an altar and so
on, there you can certainly see some type of a connection, that
things that are put on the altar may be require a blessing
and not other things. So the גמרא says ואתי נמי זית, ve'ati
nami zayit, and at most I could include olives, because you get
oil from them. דאית ביה צד מזבח, de'it beih tzad mizbeach, those
also go on the altar in the form of oil. Okay, so
that I could include, but I'm not going to expand it to
include all things. So says the גמרא, וזית מצד מזבח אתי, vezayit
mitzad mizbeach ati, are you telling me olives come from, you know,
has this aspect about you only get it because of this aspect
of going on the altar? דבהדיא כתיב ביה כרם. debahedya ketiv beih
kerem. It's included in the word of כרם kerem which we say
about the רבעי. reva'i. Where's it included in the word of כרם,
kerem. olives? דכתיב, dechtiv, the פסוק pasuk says in שופטים, Shoftim, ויבער
מגדיש ועד קמה ועד כרם זית. vayiva'er migadish ve'ad kama ve'ad kerem
zayit. He consumed
from the—from the—from the—the wheat, the bundled wheat to the standing wheat
and to the כרם kerem of the olives. So you see the
olive orchard is called a כרם. So why did you need to
learn it from this צד השוה? tzad hashaveh? It should be included
in the פסוק pasuk. about כרם רבעי. kerem reva'i. So אמר רב
פפא, amar Rav Papa, that's not a point. כרם זית איקרי כרם
סתם לא איקרי. kerem zayit ikri kerem stam lo ikri. It would
be called an olive orchard, but כרם by itself only refers to
the vine. Anyway, back to our point, מכל מקום קשיא, mikol makom
kashya, we still have our challenge, that at most you get olives—at
most you get grapes and wheat and things that are similar that
go on the altar. מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן יש בו צד
מזבח. mah lehatzad hashaveh shebahen shekein yesh bo tzad mizbeach. Maybe you
only make blessings on things that go on the altar. So how
do you know you make blessings on all foods? So the גמרא
says אלא דיליף לה משבעת המינים. ela deyalif lah mishivat haminim. Let's
learn it from the seven species. Here's the question about when the
פסוק pasuk says you make a ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon... ואכלת ושבעת
וברכת, v'achalta v'savata uverachta, on what things? So right before the פסוק
pasuk, said, you know, it's this land, you know, ארץ חטה ושעורה
ארץ גפן ותאנה ורמון. eretz chitah us'orah eretz gephen ute'einah verimon. Wait
a minute, excuse me, ארץ זית שמן ודבש. eretz zayit shemen udevash.
I'm losing the פסוק. pasuk,
Anyway,
and then it says ארץ אשר לא במסכנות תאכל בה לחם לא
תחסר כל בה. eretz asher lo vemiskeinut tochal bah lechem lo techsar
kol bah. Right? So לחם, lechem, לא תחסר כל בה. lo techsar
kol bah. Anyway, thank you. So anyway, so it speaks about the
שבעת המינים, shivat haminim, about the seven species, and it also speaks
about bread. So when we say ואכלת ושבעת, v'achalta v'savata, is it
going on bread, what the גמרא assumed before, קמה, kama, wheat, bread,
or is it going on all the שבעת המינים? shivat haminim? So
here the גמרא says let's say it's going on all the שבעת
המינים. shivat haminim. Biblically you have to make a ברכה beracha at
the end for all the שבעת המינים. shivat haminim. And we now
have a קל וחומר. If you make a ברכה at the end,
you make it at the beginning. So now we have a beginning
ברכה for all the שבעת המינים. shivat haminim. So maybe that is
a broad enough category to include everything. So the גמרא says מה
לשבעת המינים דבר שנהנה וטעון ברכה, mah lishivat haminim davar sheneheneh veta'un
berakhah, the same way these are things you derive benefit and you
get a ברכה, אף כל דבר שנהנה וטעון ברכה, af kol davar
sheneheneh veta'un berakhah, all things as well that you derive benefit get
a ברכה. No, מה לשבעת המינים שכן חייבין בביכורים. mah lishivat haminim
shekein chayavin be-vikurim. Those also have a distinctive category: you only bring
ביכורים bikurim from those and not from other things. And again, ביכורים
bikurim also has this idea you bring it to the—to the מקדש,
Mikdash, you say words of praise. So I think this idea of
צד מזבח tzad mizbeach and ביכורים. bikurim. is very interesting in terms
of the idea of a ברכה, sort of like the re-living of
the מקדש Mikdash experience of saying praise over the food that you
are offering to God. So now the Gemara says ועוד היתני לאחריו,
ve'od hatenei leachrav, all of that would only tell you afterwards. לפניו
מניין, going back to that point, how do you know before? All
this is about blessings afterwards. So it says what it said before,
הא לא קשיא, lo kashya, that's not a problem. דאתי בקל וחומר,
we make the קל וחומר, כשהוא שבע מברך כשהוא רעב לא כל
שכן, if you make it when you're sated, how much more so
you should make it when you're hungry. So now we're still limited
though, fine, maybe we have blessings before and after for שבעת המינים.
shivat haminim. But how do you know about everything? And now the
Gemara says ולמאן דתני נדבה, uleman detani nedva, even if you say
that פסוק pasuk. before that we learned the ברכה afterwards, הילולים, hilulim,
is not limited to wine and applies to all things that are
planted, תינח כל דבר נטיעה, teineih kol dvar neti'ah,
that's things that are sort of planted. דלאו
בר נטיעה, delav bar neti'ah, things that aren't planted, כגון, kegon, here
you go David, בשר ביצים ודגים, basar beitzim vedagim,
meat, eggs, and fish. By the way, the reason it doesn't mention
milk is that it was not until very recent times that we
started drinking milk as a food. Okay, they had
cheese and yogurt, but they, milk was not a drink until very
recent times. Anyway, so how about those? That you can't get it
all from this פסוק, pasuk those don't come from the ground. And
by the way, you know, that sense of sort of appreciating God's
blessings is so much more powerful by the things that come from
the earth, right? The need for the rain, the praying for the
rain, the sense that there's sort of, you plant it, you don't
see it, and then somehow miraculously a few months later it comes
out of the ground. So that's maybe ברכות berachot are limited to
things that are coming from the earth, don't apply to other things.
So אלא, ela, the Gemara says fine, forget everything we just said,
it's not based on קודש הילולים, kodesh hilulim, אלא סברא הוא, ela
sevara hu, it's logic. אסור לו לאדם שיהנה מן העולם הזה בלא
ברכה, assur lo leadam sheyehene min ha'olam hazeh belo berachah, which seems
to echo back what Rabbi Akiva said, which is you cannot be
getting benefit, which sort of what the Gemara says דבר שנהנה טעון
ברכה, you cannot be getting benefit until you give a blessing to
God. But there's a difference in emphasis, right? Until now the emphasis
has been, you know, we have to thank God for our blessings.
So maybe we could have just limited to a blessing afterwards. Maybe,
you know, okay, maybe also before as the Gemara says we are
more appreciative before, but it's not like you have to make the
blessing in order to allow you to eat the food. It's the
fact that you're about to eat the food obligates you to make
a blessing. If you ate the food and didn't make a blessing
according to the first approach, you would have not given the right
praise to God, but you wouldn't have somehow done something forbidden in
terms of eating food you weren't entitled to eat, right? There the
emphasis was about the הילולים hilulim is praising God for our blessings.
Here the emphasis is they're not entitled until you have acknowledged that
they come from God and that's a sort of different emphasis. Now
I do want to say something about this issue. So by the
way, mostly that's assumed that now we have abandoned the idea that
this could be biblical, it's rabbinic, although sometimes we say that if
logic dictates that has a biblical quality to it as well. But
again the Gemara has abandoned the קל וחומר and assumes that it's
rabbinic. The other important point to make is that if you look
at the very first Tosafot, כיצד מברכין, keitzad mevarechin, if you remember
when we started the מסכת, masechet, we said like where does, why
does the Mishnah assume we're saying שמע? Shema? So Tosafot says, if
you look at the first Tosafot, he said לא שייך להקשות תנא
היכא קאי דקתני כיצד. lo shayakh lehakshot tana heicha kai d'katani keitzad.
Why does it assume we're making ברכות? berachot? Why doesn't it start
by telling us that we're obligated to make ברכות? berachot? כדפרך בריש
מכילתין. kidefarach bereish mekhiltin. משום דהכא סברא הוא לברך, mishum dehacha sevara
hu levarech, כדמסיק בגמרא, kemadsik begemara, אסור לו לאדם שיהנה מן העולם
הזה בלא ברכה. assur lo leadam sheyehene min ha'olam hazeh belo berachah.
So he says we didn't say how do you know you have
to make ברכות, berachot, of course you make ברכות, berachot, it would
be, of course you can't eat God's gifts without giving blessings over
them. So it's quite ironic I would say according to Tosafot that
we don't take it for granted that you say שמע Shema although
it's a פסוק, pasuk although you know it's the rabbinic interpretation of
the פסוק. pasuk There the Gemara has to say why didn't you
first, why did you just start asking when you say שמע, Shema,
tell us that you have to, how do I know you say
it? Here it's taken for granted that of course you make ברכות
berachot before you eat, you would not be deriving benefit without making
a ברכה. And now the Gemara shifts to that emphasis of not
just the praising but making the ברכה to allow us to eat.
So let's take a look. If you take a look by the
way just to one final point, the bottom Tosafot of the דף,
daf, אלא סברא הוא אסור לאדם שיהנה, ela sevara hu assur leadam
sheyehene, וקרא דנסיב לעיל ukra de'nassiv le'eil when he used the verse
of הילולים, hilulim, אסמכתא בעלמא, asmachta be'alma, that's just a, you're using
a פסוק pasuk but it's not really biblical. והגמרא הוה סברה מתחילה
לימוד גמור הוא, vehagemara hava savra me'itchila limud gamur hu, originally the
Gemara thought it was really biblical, this idea of making blessings beforehand.
Now we come to the conclusion that it's this concept about not
deriving benefit but not necessarily this biblical idea. Yes.
So at this point we're saying that the ברכה before is just
sort of a סברא. sevara. Yes.
It's strangely so light comparatively is even אסור. assur. Right. But then
afterwards the ברכת המזון...
Birkat Hamazon we're not worrying about ברכת המזון right now. No, that
we'll worry about later. Now we're doing ברכה before. The only reason
we introduced ברכה after was to get to the ברכה before. That's
our focus now. Let's take a look at the Gemara. תנו רבנן:
Tanu rabbanan: אסור לו לאדם שיהנה מן העולם הזה בלא ברכה. assur
lo leadam sheyehene min ha'olam hazeh belo berachah. It is forbidden for
a person to derive benefit from this world without a blessing. And
now it takes it one step further. וכל הנהנה מן העולם הזה
בלא ברכה מעל, vekhol hanehene min ha'olam hazeh belo berachah ma'al, if
you derive benefit without a blessing it is like you have transgressed
מעילה, me'ilah, which is the... prohibition of deriving benefit from sanctified objects.
Now this is very powerful, right? It says that everything in this
world belongs to God. It's all God's property, so if God's property,
it's all sanctified. Anything owned by the Temple is sanctified and you
can't use it for yourself. So the world belongs to God and
to use it without getting permission, which is now what the ברכה
is, is a way of deriving benefit, theft of God's property, which
is מעילה, me'ilah, which is transgression of sanctified objects. Right, exactly. Now,
the I do want to mention before we continue that both in
the first stage and here we are having a very interesting introduction
of a concept of קדושה kedusha into our eating. Right? The first
stage has the model of like הלולים like the same way you
bring food and you give praise when you bring food and you
bring the ביכורים bikurim and you bring the נטע רבעי neta revai
and you sing over it and you bring the wine we mentioned.
So it's a type of a praising over food evokes the way
in which this was done in the מקדש, mikdash, somewhat type of
a reliving of a מקדש mikdash experience, sanctifying our eating that way.
Here, it's also sanctifying by saying all food is God's and therefore
to allow you to eat it you have you have to approach
it acknowledging that it is all God's and bringing sanctity into, you
know, every every moment of our lives essentially is what it's doing,
that even our most mundane life and the most mundane activity of
eating is something that acknowledges the fundamental sanctity of the act of
ברכה and even of the food itself. So now the גמרא says
מאי תקנתיה, mai takantei, so what do you do if you benefited
and you were מועל, moel, how do you fix that up? So
ילך אצל חכם, yelech etzel chacham, go to a go to a
sage. So the גמרא says ילך אצל חכם, yelech etzel chacham, go
to a sage? מאי עביד ליה? mai avid lei? How's he going
to help you? הא אבי איסורא, ha avi issura, you've already transgressed,
you've been מועל. moel. So the גמרא says אלא אמר רבא ילך
אצל חכם מעיקרא, ela amar Rava yelech etzel chacham me'ikara, you should
first go to a sage ahead of time and
וילמדנו ברכות v'yilamdenu brachot and he'll teach you all the ברכות brachot
כדי שלא יבוא לידי מעילה k'dei shelo yavo lidei me'ilah so you
do not come to מעילה. me'ilah. And why do we say this
more than other things? So the מהרש"א Maharsha says, you know, because
ברכות brachot is a really hard category to learn. It's one thing
to learn the text of שמע, Shema, wonderful, but it's another thing
to go learn all of the different types of foods you can
have and all the different possible ברכות. brachot. I mean, that's why
they have ברכה bees in all of these schools because it's not
trivial to learn all the where you what types of ברכות brachot
you make on all these different things. So you really have to
spend time if you want to be sensitive to this issue. Because
what the מהרש"א Maharsha adds and that's not so much the פשט
is that he says because if you make the even if you
make the wrong ברכה, if you're not יוצא, yotzei, you're still מועל.
moel. If you made a שהכל shehakol you'd be יוצא, yotzei, but
if you made העץ ha'etz when it had to be האדמה, ha'adamah,
you wouldn't be יוצא, yotzei, so you'd also have the מועל moel
problem, which I don't know if the גמרא is point. The גמרא
is not yet getting to that level of detail, but anyway this
is the idea of מועל. moel. So now the גמרא says let's
just move on. Mah גמרא says okay, וילמדנו כדי שלא יבוא לידי
מעילה. v'yilamdenu k'dei shelo yavo lidei me'ilah. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
כל הנהנה מן העולם הזה בלא ברכה כאילו נהנה מקדשי שמים, amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel kol haneheneh min ha'olam hazeh b'lo bracha k'ilu
neheneh mikodshei shamayim,
which seems to just be a different way of reframing the מעילה,
me'ilah, that you have benefited from things sanctified by heaven. שנאמר לה'
הארץ ומלואה, shene'emar la'Hashem ha'aretz umlo'ah, it's all God's. ורבי לוי רמי,
v'Rabbi Levi rami, Rabbi Levi showed a contradiction. כתיב לה' הארץ ומלואה,
ksiv la'Hashem ha'aretz umlo'ah, the land is God's, the land and its
fill belongs to God. וכתיב v'chsiv the other פסוק pasuk says השמים
שמים לה' והארץ נתן לבני אדם, hashamayim shamayim la'Hashem v'ha'aretz natan livnei
adam,
the heavens are God's, he's given us the land. So לא קשיא,
Lo kashya. it's not difficult. כאן קודם ברכה כאן לאחר ברכה, kan
kodem bracha kan l'achar bracha, before after the blessing. If we acknowledge
that it is a gift from God, then we have a license
to use it. Once we have acknowledged that this belongs to God.
But without acknowledging that it's God's, then we are taking something that
fundamentally does not belong to us. We're given it as one of
God's blessings and if we acknowledge it as a God's blessing, you
know, then we are then we have license to use it. One
minute can I just ask?
What? Can you repeat the last point one second?
Pete thoughts, let me read let me get to the dots and
then I'll take some comments. אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא כל הנהנה
מן העולם הזה בלא ברכה כאילו גוזל להקדוש ברוך הוא וכנסת ישראל.
amar Rabbi Chanina bar Papa kol haneheneh min ha'olam hazeh b'lo bracha
k'ilu gozel l'haKadosh Baruch Hu u'knesset Yisrael. It's like you're stealing, by
what seems to be less than the מעילה, me'ilah, מעילה me'ilah seems
to include the idea of stealing, but okay here we're emphasizing that
more so that sec- not necessarily sanctity aspect, but you're just taking
something that isn't yours and from the Jewish people. Why the Jewish
people are mentioned in a minute. שנאמר גוזל אביו ואמו, shene'emar gozel
aviv v'imo, you steal from your father and mother, ואומר אין פשע,
v'omer ein pasha, it's no sin. חבר הוא לאיש משחית, chaver hu
l'ish mashchit, such a person is a colleague to a destructive man.
ואין אביו אלא הקדוש ברוך הוא, v'ein aviv ela haKadosh Baruch Hu,
the father is God, שנאמר הלוא הוא אביך קנך, shene'emar halo hu
avicha kanecha, he is your father who created you. ואין אמו אלא
כנסת ישראל, v'ein imo ela knesset Yisrael, the mother is the Jewish
people, שנאמר שמע בני מוסר אביך ואל תטוש תורת אמך. shene'emar shma
bni musar avicha v'al titosh torat imecha. I don't know how we
know that's כנסת ישראל, knesset Yisrael, but okay, that's כנסת ישראל. knesset
Yisrael. So and therefore you say אין פשע, ein pasha, which basically
means you tell people it's no big deal I didn't make a
ברכה, big deal. And then and the way רש"י Rashi explains it
is, so if you go ahead and and through your actions demonstrate
to people that making a ברכה is trivial and not something to
worry about, they'll learn from you and they'll also treat it lightly
and then you will sort of spread spread this, you know, bad
behavior amongst others as well. So מאי חבר הוא לאיש משחית, mai
chaver hu l'ish mashchit, what does it mean to become a colleague
to a destructive
person? אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא חבר הוא לירבעם amar Rabbi Chanina
bar Papa chaver hu l'Yeravam ירבעם בן נבט. Yerovam ben Nevat. You
become a colleague to ירבעם בן נבט Yerovam ben Nevat who was
the one that split בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael into
two, שהשחית את ישראל לאביהם שבשמים, she-hishchis et Yisrael l'Avihem she-ba-shamayim, he
corrupted them, he took them away from God. Now again that seems
extreme, it obviously is extreme, but think for a minute again about
the מקדש Mikdash theme. What did he do? He prevented people from
being עולה לרגל. oleh l'regel. He took them away from the מקדש,
Mikdash, he took them away from connecting to God and bringing their
products, right? Because what we haven't mentioned, which was mentioned before, was
also the animals, bringing the grain and the wine and the oil
and the animals and bringing all of those into the מקדש Mikdash
and you know, in acknowledgment and thanks to God in the מקדש.
Mikdash. So again what I see very much here is repeating this
theme about how we have brought sanctity into our eating, that we
acknowledge that all the food is God's and it's sanctified and we
only by blessing do we have license then to use it for
ourselves. And the other is that the process of giving a blessing
somewhat echoes the process of bringing the food, bringing פתח הלל, pasach
Hallel, bringing שירה, shirah, bringing קרבנות, korbanos, bringing this to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash and saying words of prayer and the sanctity in
that act, in that act. And that's why somebody who leads somebody
away from ברכות berachos is like ירבעם בן נבט Yerovam ben Nevat
who took ישראל Yisrael totally away from the מקדש. Mikdash. You steal
the sanctity of our daily lives if you remove the ברכות berachos
that we make over the food. David, you wanted to say something.
Yeah, not that I have any objections to somebody's conversation, yes, but
it does seem that the פסוק says that the שמים שמים לה'
והארץ נתן לבני אדם shamayim shamayim l'Hashem v'ha'aretz nasan livnei adam suggests
a past act of gift, right? And then why does the produce
any longer
belong to God?
If it's been a gift and it has been given, it said
נתן לבני אדם, nasan livnei adam, right? So the issue is really
an important issue in this גמרא because it's showing the title.
So that's a good point. I mean look,
שמים שמים לה'... shamayim shamayim l'Hashem... הארץ ומלואה ha'aretz u'mlo'ah also a
current state. So they're both in contradiction, right? What? No, but the
contradiction is what's brought. How do you... so the way to answer
that I would say would be is yes, we've been given it
as a gift, but somewhat you know
we're...
it's not that we're only given it once we are... once we
make the ברכה. We've been given the land, but we're somehow only
entitled...
I have an idea.
Go ahead. I mean yeah.
The concept of private property is not the one that we have
here. There's no such thing as total private ownership in Judaism. Everything
really belongs to God.
Like the שמיטה shemittah idea. Right. I mean thank you. I mean
that's
where I was just thinking, you know, it's like the שמיטה shemittah
idea, right? You... the land reverts, right, at... not שמיטה, shemittah, יובל,
Yovel, because כי לי כל הארץ. ki li kol ha'aretz. What do
you mean כי לי כל הארץ? ki li kol ha'aretz? What are
we doing with having all these laws about מקח וממכר mekach u'memkar
and slaves and all these things, you know, if it's not ours
to begin with? So it's some sort of fundamental level, it's all
God, even though we're given rights to use it and we're able
to treat it as ours. And I think that's what the גמרא
is saying here that... that our rights to use it are contingent
on our fundamental acknowledgment. It's not like we're only given it after
that fact. They're both true at the same time. Yes.
So you were saying before the גמרא seems to be a big...
like a personal dig at other רבנן rabbanan that you must listen,
continue listening to their ways and you mentioned he was like a
heretic or something like that... so it's like sort of an internal
argument that you have to... תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh mainly,
how the Jewish people
traditionally observe this, and then you said...
I don't know if I... I didn't say heretic. I think you
must have misheard me. So I wasn't talking about...
but I mean, you have to listen to the rabbinic because they
established...
Yeah, but we're not emphasizing here rabbinic authority, I mean, implicitly this
is a rabbinic law, but that's not the emphasis here.
Yeah. What I was going to say was, it's one thing to
say, you know, that you're doing something wrong, but you're comparing someone
to ירבעם בן נבט Yerovam ben Nevat who's מחטיא את הרבים. machti
et ha-rabbim. And he's supposedly... he's not making his own ברכה.
No, no, that's why I said before that it says ואומר אין
פשע. v'omer ein pesha. You go ahead saying, yeah, it's not a
big deal, don't have to worry about ברכות, berachos, it's trivial. So
then you're misleading other people. It's not just you. By going around
and announcing it's no big deal, you are being מחטיא את הרבים.
machti et ha-rabbim. That's the way it's explained. Right.
But if I just didn't make my own
ברכה, right, then we're not... Now what is... what is stealing from
כנסת ישראל? Knesset Yisrael? So there רש"י Rashi says, and this is
an idea that we really haven't introduced, that by that the ברכות,
berachos, making the ברכה, bring future blessing. And that might be also
echoing the פסוקים pesukim from the נטע רבעי neta revai which is
that if you go ahead and you bring it and קודש הלולים,
kodesh hillulim, then in the future הוסף לכם תבואתו, yosef lachem tvu'aso,
that that leads then to greater increase in the following years. So
that's a new idea as well, that acknowledging God through the food,
you know, is part of the continued blessing of the land. And
therefore by stealing, you're also stealing from כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael because
then the fruit do not receive that ongoing blessing. So this does
very much
evoke sort of biblical and מקדש Mikdash types of ideas. You bring
the food, you give thanks, you give
acknowledgment.
Why do you have to use the Rabbinic language to thank God?
Why can't you just say thank you, God?
So that's a question about everything. Why do you have to use
the Rabbinic language to say שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei?
They are asserting themselves. The תורה Torah says you eat, you thank.
The תורה Torah doesn't say you make a ברכה before and after.
So then they derived you make a
ברכה. But why restrict it and say you have
to use this language?
Why can't you just say thank you?
Okay, you could just say thank you. First of all, it
counts biblically because biblically there is no obligation. The Rabbis are the
ones that said you make a ברכה and they get to say
what text to use. Now we will find out later that there
is a certain amount of latitude in the text. You can say,
you know, slightly rewrite it, paraphrase it, translate it and so on.
We will find that later. Okay, but again it's like the question,
you know, that I think Rachel asked a few weeks ago: Well
if I pray to God, what difference does it make if I
say the שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? I'm praying to God. Yes, you
are doing the profound human religious experience of praying to God, of
thanking God, of acknowledging God. All of that you're doing. What you're
not doing is the Rabbinic obligation of prayer. Okay, so if you
don't want to worry about the Rabbinic obligation of prayer then you've
definitely done the meaningful religious experience here. But there still is the
Rabbis who created it as an obligation, which wasn't in the verse,
they've also defined what are the parameters. Okay, so all right let's
keep on going. אביי, Abaye, I know, we'll get back to you
in a minute. רבי חנינא בר פפא. Rabbi Chanina bar Papa. רבי
חנינא בר פפא Rabbi Chanina bar Papa says: רמי, Rami, see one
verse says ולקחתי דגני בעתו. ve-lakachti degani be-ito. I will take my
grain in its time. If you sin I'll take back my grain,
I'll assert my ownership, says God. וכתיב, U-ketiv, but the פסוק by
the שמע Shema says ואספת דגנך, ve-asafta deganecha, you'll gather in your
grain. So there's an obvious answer: לא קשיא. כאן בזמן שישראל עושים
רצונו של מקום כאן בזמן שאין ישראל עושים רצונו של מקום. Kan
bi-zman she-Yisrael osim ritzono shel Makom, kan bi-zman she-ein Yisrael osim ritzono
shel Makom. In fact it's the reverse in terms of the order
of the פסוקים. pesukim. When we listen to God we gather in
our grain. When we don't listen to God then God reasserts God's
ownership and God takes the grain back and we do not get
the benefit from the grain.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, going back also to maybe David's point as
well, that God's gift is ongoing. The land is one thing, the
produce it always is, you know, it's always hanging whether what will
happen to the produce. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, ואספת דגנך, ve-asafta deganecha,
gather your grain. מה תלמוד לומר? Mah talmud lomar? What does that
teach us? לפי שנאמר, Le-phi she-ne'emar, the verse
says לא ימוש ספר התורה הזה מפיך, lo yamush sefer ha-Torah ha-zeh
mi-picha, that to the beginning of the book of יהושע, Yehoshua, God
says to יהושע: Yehoshua: This book of תורה Torah shall not stray
from your lips, from your mouth, והגית בו יומם ולילה, ve-hagita bo
yomam va-layla, you shall toil in it day and night. So יכול
דברים ככתבן? yakhol devarim kichtavan? Maybe it's literal? Maybe we should not
do anything in our lives other than learn תורה? Torah? Learn תורה
Torah every second? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: ואספת דגנך. ve-asafta deganecha. No,
you have to gather in your grain too. הנהג בהן מנהג דרך
ארץ. Hanhag ba-hen minhag derech eretz. With תורה Torah you have to
have דרך ארץ, derech eretz, you have to have the way of
the land, you have to make a living together with תורה. Torah.
You don't learn תורה Torah every minute. דברי רבי ישמעאל. Divrei Rabbi
Yishmael. That's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael's approach. רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai, remember רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai
went into the cave, right? To not have much patience for the
common person who was involved in normal activities about making a living
and so on. It was all about תורה Torah for him. So
let's see what he says. אומר: Omer: אפשר? Efshar? אדם, Adam, is
it possible a person
חורש בשעת חרישה, choresh bi-sh'at charisha, plow at the time of
plowing, thank you, plow the time of plowing, וזורע בשעת זריעה, ve-zore'a
bi-sh'at zri'a, seed at the time of planting seed, וקוצר בשעת קצירה,
ve-kotzer bi-sh'at ktzira, harvest at the time of harvesting, ודש בשעת דישה,
ve-dash bi-sh'at disha, and thresh at the time of threshing, וזורה בשעת
הרוח, ve-zoreh bi-sh'at ha-ruach, and winnow at the time when it's windy.
So if this is what you're spending your time in, תורה מה
תהא עליה? Torah mah te-hei aleiha? What's going to be with תורה?
Torah? When are you ever going to have a chance to learn
seriously? אלא, Ela, בזמן שישראל עושים רצונו של מקום, bi-zman she-Yisrael osim
ritzono shel Makom, if you're doing God's will, מלאכתן נעשית על ידי
אחרים. melachtan na'asit al yedei acherim. Then other people will take care
of you. You sit and learn, other people will go ahead and
they'll somehow support you, their word will get your work will get
done through them. שנאמר: She-ne'emar: ועמדו זרים ורעו צאנכם, ve-amdu zarim ve-ra'u
tzonechem, foreigners will stand up and they'll shepherd your sheep. ובזמן שאין
ישראל עושים רצונו של מקום, U-bi-zman she-ein Yisrael osim ritzono shel Makom,
when you're not doing the will of God, מלאכתן נעשית על ידי
עצמן. melachtan na'asit al yedei atzman. Then you've got to do it
for yourself. שנאמר: She-ne'emar: ואספת דגנך, ve-asafta deganecha,
you'll gather your grain. ולא עוד, Ve-lo od, not only that, אלא
מלאכת אחרים נעשית על ידן, ela melachet acherim na'asit al yadan,
you'll have to work for others. שנאמר: She-ne'emar: ועבדת את
אויביך. ve-avadeta et oyevecha. Anyway you'll serve your enemies.
Right, good. ואמר אביי: Ve-amar Abaye: So now אביי Abaye said, what's
the wrap up of this? הרבה עשו כרבי ישמעאל ועלתה בידן. Harbe
asu ke-Rabbi Yishmael ve-alta be-yadan. Many people followed רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael's
teaching and it was successful. They were able to make a living
and they were able to learn תורה. Torah. כרבי שמעון בר יוחאי,
ke-Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, many people tried to follow רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai's approach and just spend their time learning
תורה, Torah, ולא עלתה בידן, ve-lo alta be-yadan, it was not successful.
Now what does it mean not successful? Does it mean that they
didn't have any food? It didn't work out that
מלאכתן נעשית על ידי אחרים melachtan na'asit al yedei acherim and that...
Maybe it also means that their תורה Torah wasn't successful. If they're
not able to support themselves, maybe in the end it also meant
that their תורה Torah wasn't successful either. So אמר ליה רבא לרבנן,
amar lei Rava l'rabanan, so now Rava said to the Rabbis, במטותא
מינייכו, b'matusa minaichu,
you know, please, with your leave, ביומי ניסן וביומי תשרי לא תחזו
קמאי. b'yomei nisan u'vyomei tishrei lo sechezu kamai. I don't want to
see you here in the ישיבה yeshiva during Nissan and Tishrei. Okay,
why? Because you should be home with your families during the ימים
טובים? yamim tovim? No. He says כי היכי דלא תטרדו במזונייכו כולי
שתא. ki heichi d'lo tistardu b'mezonaychu kulei shata.
Tishrei and Nissan are the times of planting and harvesting. So you
know what? Take off from ישיבה, yeshiva, spend those two months doing
some serious, you know, some serious work in the fields, and then
you'll have the freedom to learn the other ten months out of
the year. So the point is, now that's not exactly, that's maybe
a compromise implicitly with the רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai. Ten months out of the year you're learning, but two months
you have to devote towards just focusing on doing the work that's
hopefully will support you for the rest of the year if you
can be that successful. So I got I want to say a
couple of things about this. Number one is,
now they all flew from my head. Okay, so, ah, so, so
this issue about הרבה עשו ולא עלתה בידם, harbe asu v'lo alsah
b'yadam, so first of all, I just have to say something. This
idea of working a few months to support you for the rest
of the year, you know, you have this a lot like people
in Israel, some types of like a lot of מחנכים mechanchim in
Israel that don't make any money, they come to the States for
the summer, they make enough money it helps them for the rest
of the year. Somebody once called this phenomenon המוציא לחם מחוץ לארץ,
hamotzi lechem michutz la'aretz,
which I thought was particularly appropriate for what we're learning here. But
anyway, so you know obviously this gets to this question about spending
all your time learning in ישיבה, yeshiva, you know, getting a פרנסה,
parnassah, when is it appropriate? There's a lot to be said about
that. There's a רמב"ם, Rambam, you know, on פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot
and in משנה תורה Mishneh Torah that goes at great length critiquing
people that sit and learn all day and think that it's other
people's responsibility to support them. At the same time, the רמב"ם Rambam
at the end of שמיטה ויובל, Shemitah v'Yovel, you know, says that
if somebody who devotes themselves completely to knowing God and spending their
energies just learning and knowing God, you know, and frees themselves from
all of the nonsense of the world and the worry about making
a living and all of that, you know, that person, you know,
is sanctified קודש קדשים. kodesh kodashim. He doesn't say how the person
will make a living, but anyway, he seems to hold that out
as an ideal. And that often is the way these two extremes
are expressed. And the מהרש"א Maharsha says it very nicely. He says
that the problem with רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai
with the people that followed and it was not successful was that
הרבה עשו כרבי שמעון בר יוחאי. harbe asu k'Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai.
רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai as a holding out
might be an ideal for like, you know, a very tiny number
of people. There are some people, you know, maybe the community should
support. I mean, you know, we pay for people, you know, we
give them postdocs and whatever and we give, you know, funds for
people in liberal arts and other areas in which they can't make
money, but we feel it's something that's contributing to the society. You
know, funds that are given to the arts and whatever. We used
to give them. We don't give them any money anymore. Okay, okay,
anyway, so much for that. But the point is, maybe there are
a few people that we should be giving societal funds because of
what they can contribute. But those are, those are very small in
number. Those are your רבי שמעון בר יוחאיs. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai
Everybody else, the הרבה עשו harbe asu is the רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Ishmael, and you know, as the מהרש"א Maharsha also points out, you
can't say it's really not עושים רצונו של מקום, osim retzono shel
makom, it's in the פסוק of the שמע, Shema, ואספת דגנך. v'asafta
deganecha. It's ואהבת את ה' אלוהיך, v'ahavta es Hashem Elokecha, you know,
talking about you love God and you do all the מצוות mitzvos
and then it says ואספת דגנך, v'asafta deganecha, you'll gather in the
grain. So this is people that are really, you know, this is
an ideal for most people. It's not the ideal for a very
small number of people. Very small number of people, that is the
רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. As it says, רבא,
Rava, אביי Abaye might be trying to strike a balance, רבא Rava
might be trying to strike a balance to says, you know, how
exactly you divide the day. Like when the רמב"ם Rambam speaks about,
the רמב"ם Rambam who says everybody has to work, says how do
you divide your time? He says, well, let's say you have twelve
hours of daylight. So you spend nine hours learning and three hours
working. And you know with the nine hours, here's how you divide
those nine hours of learning. So you know there's a question even
if you're going to work how much time. Of course not everybody
has the leisure of being able to spend a few hours and
support or a few months and supporting themselves for the rest of
the year. So now let's see where the גמרא continues. אמר רבה
בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן משום
רבי יהודה ברבי אלעאי. Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan
mishum Rabbi Yehuda b'rebi Ilai. So בוא וראה שלא כדורות הראשונים דורות
האחרונים. bo u'rei shelo k'doros harishonim doros ha'acharonim. See that the later
generations are not like the earlier generations. דורות הראשונים עשו תורתן קבע
ומלאכתן עראי. doros harishonim asu Torasan keva u'melachtan arai. Exactly sort of
fitting into the point I was making, which is the earlier generations,
yes they worked. Okay, they did the רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, they
did the ואספת דגנך. v'asafta deganecha. But their תורה Torah was the
focus of their lives and the מלאכה melacha was something that they
did, you know, because they had to make a living. It wasn't
how they defined themselves. Okay, and it wasn't what they maybe spent
the majority of their time doing. וזו וזו נתקיימו בידם, v'zo v'zo
niskaymu b'yadam, they managed to make a living and they managed to
really succeed in תורה. Torah. דורות האחרונים, doros ha'acharonim, later generations, שעשו
מלאכתן קבע ותורתן עראי, she'asu melachtan keva v'Torasan arai, they make their
work their primary endeavor, you know, when we define ourselves, we define
it by what job we have in our work and that's our
primary endeavor. endeavor in
time, in focus, and identity. And when we get some extra time
we learn תורה. Torah. וזו וזו לא נתקיימה בידם. Zu ve-zu lo
niskayma b'yadam. You know what? They don't wind up making a good
living and they certainly don't wind up learning a lot of תורה.
Torah. Okay, so whether that always works out that way, but that's
at least a critique of you know this idea of where do
we emphasize in terms of our time and our identity and what
is קבע keva our lives and what is עראי. arai. ואמר רבה
בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יהודה ברבי אלעאי, Ve'amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yehuda b'Rabbi Ilai,
בוא וראה שלא כדורות הראשונים דורות האחרונים. Bo urei shelo kedoros harishonim
doros ha'achronim. The earlier generations are not like the later ones, or
the later ones are not like the earlier ones. דורות הראשונים, Doros
harishonim, the earlier ones, היו מכניסים פירותיהם דרך טרקסמון כדי לחייבם במעשר,
hayu machnisim peiroseihem derech traksmon kedei lechayevam b'maaser, would bring in their
fruit in the sort of main gate in order that they would
be obligated in מעשר, maaser, because only when you bring in your
fruit sort of through the gate, through the main opening and then
it's you know winnowed and whatever, then you take מעשר maaser from
it. דורות האחרונים מכניסים פירותיהם דרך גגות דרך חצרות דרך חפפות כדי
לפטרם מן המעשר. Doros ha'achronim machnisim peiroseihem derech gagot derech chatzerot derech
chapifot kedei lifteram min hamaaser. Later generations bring them in through the
roofs and through the yards and you know they bring them in
in the non-main entrance and that is a technicality that actually exempts
them from taking מעשר. maaser. They still can't eat אכילת קבע, achilas
keva, but they can eat it all by feeding it to their
animal, אכילת עראי, achilas arai, a temporary eating. So they find a
way to get around doing their obligations. ואמר רבי ינאי אין הטבל
מתחייב במעשר עד שיראה פני הבית, Ve'amar Rabbi Yannai ein hatevel mitchayev
b'maaser ad sheyireh pnei habayis, that the טבל tevel is not obligated
until it sees the face of the house, means comes in the
main way, שנאמר ביערתי הקודש מן הבית, Shene'emar biarti hakodesh min habayis,
I have taken out the קודש kodesh sanctified from the house. Because
it came into the house in the normal way, therefore it's obligated
in מעשר. maaser. רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו חצר קובעת, Rabbi Yochanan amar
afilu chatzer kovaas, just for a theoretical point, even if you bring
it in through the yard, that's also considered the main entrance, שנאמר
ואכלו בשעריך ושבעו, Shene'emar v'achlu bish'arecha v'savau, eating in your gates. So
not even in the house, in your gates. So some say that's
only דרבנן, but even the yards would obligate. And with this we
end this. Tomorrow we'll pick up with the next point of the
משנה Mishna about wine, but I'll say one final thing about this
about the critique about going finding a work-around, you know, is that
it's sort of very interesting that the point has to do with
focus about about wealth and money and produce and so on. So
it's דורות אחרונים doros achronim are so concerned about making מלאכתם קבע,
melachtam keva, about you know their their about their job and their
earnings and how much money they're bringing in that they that that
also becomes ways in which they find work-arounds of their other religious
obligations. It's all about the money. It's all about that's the only
thing that matters, bottom line. So that obviously is going to have
an impact on how much תורה Torah you learn and how much
you care about תורה. Torah. Has an impact on other areas of
your life as well about what you prioritize and what you allow
and what you make compromises on. Okay. See you tomorrow.